Finding Aid for G. Robert Greenberg papers, 1940-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
G. Robert Greenberg papers
1940-2005
1954-1977
Greenberg, G. Robert (1918-2005)
2014019 Aa2
G. Robert Greenberg was a professor in the Department of Biological Chemistry at Western Reserve University (1946-1957) and the University of Michigan (1957-2004). His papers contain correspondence, grant applications, research notes, and teaching documents.
4 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Material was received in September 2008 (Donor no. 10111 ).
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Goodwin Robert Greenberg was born in Danube, Minnesota on June 23, 1918. He received his B.A (1941), M.S. (1942), and Ph.D. (1944) in Biochemistry at the University of Minnesota. He was hired by Western Reserve University in 1946, and was promoted to Assistant Professor (1948) and Associate Professor of Biochemistry (1954). After receiving the American Chemical Society's Paul Lewis Award in Enzyme Chemistry, he began his career at the University of Michigan Medical School's Department of Biological Chemistry as Professor on February 15, 1957.
G. Robert Greenberg was very active in both research and teaching. His research fields included purine biosynthesis, enzymology, and molecular genetics. As a fellow at the University of Utah (1944-1946), he worked on a chemical warfare project and the anemia of infection (his chemical warfare research is not documented in this collection). Western Reserve University then recruited Greenberg to develop the new Department of Biochemistry, where his research focused on the biosynthesis of purines. Following his appointment at U-M in 1967, his research interests turned to studying bacterial viruses, studying the roles of dCMP hydroxymethylase and dTMP synthetase. He also became involved with studying bacterial genetics, researching the thymidlate synthesase in E. coli and phage ?thyA hybrids. In the 1970s, his research turned towards molecular genetics, when he worked on synthesizing deoxyribonucleotides in phage-infected cells, ultimately conducting research on membrane biochemistry with Nobel laureate Har Gobind Khorana from 1974-1975. Greenberg continued to work in molecular genetics through his appointment as Professor Emeritus in 1988 until his death, May 15, 2005.
Although predominantly a researcher, Greenberg was an active faculty member and member of the broader professional community, as a member of the American Society of Biological Chemists and American Society for Microbiology.
Greenberg first married Cora Greenberg, but divorced and later married Susan Jiga (1966). He had six children: Alice, Bettie, Efraim, Ela, James, and Paula.
The G. Robert Greenberg papers consist of four series: Biographical/Historical, Pre-University of Michigan, University of Michigan, and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Greenberg, G. Robert.; Biochemistry--Research.; Biochemistry--Study and teaching.; University of Michigan. Department of Biological Chemistry.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Greenberg, G. Robert.; Biochemistry--Study and research.; University of Michigan. Department of Biological Chemistry.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; Balls, A. K. (Arnold Kent), 1891-1966.; Smith, Arthur H. (Arthur Harry), 1893-1976.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical/Historical
  Biographical/Historical, 1957-2004 (0.2 linear feet), arranged chronologically, includes Greenberg's curriculum vitae, faculty record, and family correspondence.
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Record
    - 1957-1965 (Box 1)
    - 1976 (Box 1)
  - Family correspondence
    - 1966 (Box 1)
    - 1993-1995 (Box 1)
    - 2004 (Box 1)
- Pre-University of Michigan
  Pre-University of Michigan, 1931-1957 (0.9 linear feet) is arranged into three sub-series, Correspondence, Grants and Research, and Teaching Materials and contains records from Greenberg's work for the University of Utah and Western Reserve University. Correspondence, 1946-1957 (0.3 linear feet) consists of general and research correspondence during his tenure at Western Reserve University and his first months at the University of Michigan. Grants and Research, 1931-1957 (0.3 linear feet) consists of unpublished speeches, grant applications, and research materials. Included materials primarily focus on Greenberg's iron and anemia research. Of particular interest to researchers are the assorted lab results and lab notebooks from 1946-1956. Teaching Materials, 1946-1956 (0.3 linear feet) consists of lecture notes, exams, and other faculty meeting materials.
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence, 1946-1957; 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Lothar, 1956 (Box 1)
    - Newcastle, England sabbatical, 1956 (Box 1)
    - Research correspondence, 1947 (Box 1)
    - Wintrobe, M.M., 1946-1947 (Box 1)
    - Silverman, Milton, 1955-1956 (Box 1)
  - Grants and Research
    - Biosynthesis of Purines and Nucleic Acids, National Institute of Health Grant G-3840 and A-1111 (C3), 1953-1957 (Box 1)
    - Development of Anemia in Growing Pigs Receiving an Iron Deficient Diet, undated (Box 1)
    - Greenberg-Ashenbrucker Radio Iron Workbook, 1946 (Box 1)
    - Lab notebook
      - 1946-1947 (Box 1)
      - 1951 (Box 1)
      - 1956 (Box 1)
      - undated (Box 1)
    - Old research methods, 1931-1935 (Box 1)
    - Pathogenesis of the Anemia of Infection talk, March 14, 1947 (Box 1)
    - Phase I Lab Results, 1954 (Box 1)
    - Studies of Iron Metabolism, 1947 (Box 1)
    - Talks, Federation Meetings, Chicago, 1947-1953 (Box 1)
    - Teichoic Acids, Phosphorus-Containing Substances from Bacterial Cell Walls, paper to be read at Biochemical Congress in Vienna, undated (Box 1)
  - Teaching Materials
    - Biochemistry course materials, 1954 (Box 1)
    - Dental Biochemistry course materials, 1946-1949; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Dental Biochemistry lectures, undated (Box 1)
    - Enzymes course materials, 1954 (Box 1)
    - Lectures, 1947 (Box 1)
    - Medical lectures, undated (Box 1)
    - Nutrition lectures, undated (Box 1)
    - Pyr-Purine lectures, undated (Box 1)
    - Radioactivity Measurements lectures, undated (Box 1)
    - Western Reserve University faculty materials, 1949-1950 (Box 1)
    - Western Reserve University faculty meeting minutes, 1951-1956 (Box 1)
- University of Michigan
  University of Michigan, 1957-2005 (2.8 linear feet) is arranged into four sub-series, Correspondence, Departmental Materials, Grants and Research, and Teaching Materials. Correspondence, 1957-2005 (1.3 linear feet), arranged alphabetically and chronologically, consists of extensive incoming and outgoing correspondence with biochemists both domestically and internationally. Correspondents include alumni and leading chemists such as Nancy Nossal and Nobel laureate Har Gobind Khorana. Also of note is an autobiographical account of Greenberg's life and career in the 2005 correspondence. Departmental Materials, 1957-1995 (0.2 linear feet), arranged alphabetically, consists of records relating to the department and several University of Michigan Committees. Within this subseries, the folder Dissertation Committee includes compilations of dissertation abstracts as well as dissertation committee policies. Grants and Research, 1957-2001 (0.8 linear feet), arranged alphabetically and by grant, consists of grant applications, annual grant reports, research proposals, and records relating to his research associates. Included grant materials primarily focus on Greenberg's research into DNA, bacteriophage infection, and enzyme formation. This series includes the original 1956 grant application for Enzyme Formation in Phage-Infected Bacteria, a research project started during Greenberg's sabbatical in Newcastle, England while a member of Case Western Reserve's faculty and continued at the University of Michigan. Correspondence related to the Newcastle sabbatical is included in the Pre-University of Michigan Correspondence sub-series. The Teaching Materials sub-series, 1959-2002 (0.6 linear feet), arranged alphabetically, consists of course evaluations, exams, labs, lecture notes, and syllabi.
  - Correspondence
    - Bose, Subir K., 1964 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1958-2005; 38 folders (Box 2)
    - Correspondence with researchers, 1966 (Box 2)
    - Drake, John W., 1992-1993 (Box 2)
    - Gobind Khorana, Har, 1975-1976 (Box 2)
    - Grant correspondence, 1957-1959 (Box 2)
    - Lab correspondence, 1961-1971 (Box 2)
    - Massachusetts Institute of Technology sabbatical, 1973-1974 (Box 2)
    - National Science Foundation, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Nossal, Nancy, 1962-1963 (Box 3)
    - Research, 1968-1978; 9 folders (Box 3)
    - Research and fellowship, 1970-1976 (Box 3)
    - Shapiro, David M., 1961-1964 (Box 3)
    - SOS research, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Speaker correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 3)
  - Departmental Materials
    - Committee on Educational Affairs, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
    - Department of Biochemistry, 1966-1969 (Box 3)
    - Dissertation Committee, 1968-1973 (Box 3)
    - Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology, 1962-1963 (Box 3)
    - Molecular Genetics Center Executive Committee Meeting, May 20, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Research Training Program, undated (Box 3)
    - Symposium, 1995 (Box 3)
    - Thesis Committee meeting, January 28, 1981 (Box 3)
  - Grants and Research
    - Application for Radioisotope Procurement, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Biochemical Events after Bacteriophage Infection, National Institute of Health Grant A-1669
      - Annual expense reports, 1958-1960 (Box 3)
      - Application, 1959-1961 (Box 3)
      - Application, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
      - Grant materials, 1961-1964; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Biosynthesis and Metabolism of Nucleotides, USPHS Grant A-1669
      - Applications and budget, 1957-1961 (Box 3)
      - Budgets and employees, 1958-1962 (Box 3)
    - Characteristics of a Bacteriophage T4 Induced Complex Synthesizing Deoxyribonucleotides reader comments, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Copyright transfer agreement, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Denovo Pathway to Inosinic Acid: the Background Fifty Years Later, 2001 (Box 3)
    - Deoxyribonucleotide and DNA Biosynthesis in Phage Infection Grant Applications, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
    - Disclosure of invention, 1993 (Box 3)
    - DNA research materials, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Enzyme Formation in Phage-Infected Bacteria, National Science Foundation grant 11432
      - Employee materials, 1960-1962 (Box 3)
      - National Science Foundation correspondence, 1958-1964 (Box 3)
      - Proposal and Annual Reports, 1957-1962 (Box 3)
      - Research proposals, 1960-1964 (Box 3)
      - Sabbatical application, 1956 (Box 3)
    - Experiment protocols, 1987 (Box 3)
    - Grant applications, 1981-1982 (Box 3)
    - Grants, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - Josiah Macy Jr. Foundation Fellowship application, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Lab notebook, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Lab notes
      - 1968 (Box 3)
      - 1985 (Box 3)
    - National Institute of Health applications and correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 4)
    - Nature of DNA Replication Complex grant application, 1976 (Box 4)
    - Peer review comments
      - 1991 (Box 4)
      - undated (Box 4)
    - Phage Infected Bacteria, National Science Foundation grant 11432, 1960-1964; 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Phage Infection: Deoxyribonucleotide and DNA Biosynthesis grant application, 1975 (Box 4)
    - Research Associates
      - Al-Khalidi, Usama, 1957 (Box 4)
      - Ebisuzaki, Kaney, 1957 (Box 4)
      - Eigner, Joseph, 1961-1964 (Box 4)
      - Figueirado, Eurico, 1957-1958 (Box 4)
      - Hayes, Donal, 1957-1965 (Box 4)
      - Rodriguez, Fabio Andres, 1970-1973 (Box 4)
      - Somerville, Ronald H., 1960-1964 (Box 4)
      - Yun-chi, Yeh, 1964 (Box 4)
    - Role of Ribonucleotide Reductase in DNA Replication grant application and correspondence, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Sabbatical leave request, 1973 (Box 4)
    - Biological Chemistry 711 course evaluation, 2004 (Box 4)
    - Biological Chemistry 711 graduate seminar, 1973-1974 (Box 4)
    - Biological Chemistry 807 and 808 course materials, 1967-1969 (Box 4)
    - Biological Chemistry exams, 1959-1970; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Biological Chemistry graduate lectures, 1963 (Box 4)
    - Course 516B lab notes, 1975-1976 (Box 4)
    - Course syllabi, 1982 (Box 4)
    - Course syllabi and labs, 1974-1979; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Genetic lectures notebook, June 1964 (Box 4)
    - Massachusetts Institute of Technology sabbatical, 1974-1975 (Box 4)
    - Seminar notebook, 2002 (Box 4)
- Visual Materials
  Visual Materials, 1940-1957 (0.1 linear feet), arranged alphabetically, consists of photographs and research negatives. The photographs include the Paul Lewis Award ceremony and several Department of Biochemistry photographs dating from before Greenberg's involvement at U-M. These photographs include autographed headshots of biophysicists as well as a group department photograph from May 4, 1940.
  - American Chemical Society Paul Lewis Award photograph, 1957 (Box 4)
  - NrdB negatives, before, 1983 undated (Box 4)
  - University of Michigan Department of Biochemistry department photographs, 1940 (Box 4)